<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sacramentorum encomium: or The praise of the sacraments in a letter written in the year 1654 to the preacher then at Barham in the county of Kent, with-holding the holy sacraments from a great number of godly souls, unless they would subject themselves against laws and good conscience to a rigid Presbyterian government. Wherein the said government is plainly and undeniably proved to be (of all other) the most injurious to the magistrate, most oppressive to the subject, &amp;c. Published by a member of the parish of Barham, for the satisfaction of all wel-affected subjects, and good Christians.</title>
            <author>Member of the parish of Barnham.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S223B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219820</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831267</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831267</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35730</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58941)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35730)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2041:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sacramentorum encomium: or The praise of the sacraments in a letter written in the year 1654 to the preacher then at Barham in the county of Kent, with-holding the holy sacraments from a great number of godly souls, unless they would subject themselves against laws and good conscience to a rigid Presbyterian government. Wherein the said government is plainly and undeniably proved to be (of all other) the most injurious to the magistrate, most oppressive to the subject, &amp;c. Published by a member of the parish of Barham, for the satisfaction of all wel-affected subjects, and good Christians.</title>
                  <author>Member of the parish of Barnham.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sacraments --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35730:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacramentorum Encomium:</hi> OR THE PRAISE OF THE SACRAMENTS: IN A LETTER written in the Year 1654 to the Preacher then at <hi>Barham</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> with-holding the Holy SACRAMENTS from a great number of godly ſouls, unleſs they would ſubject themſelves againſt Laws and good Conſcience to a Rigid PRESBYTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIAN GOVERNMENT. Wherein the ſaid Government is plainly and undeniably proved to be (of all other) the moſt Injurious to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, moſt oppreſſive to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by a Member of the Pariſh of <hi>Barham,</hi> for the ſatisfaction of all Wel-affected Subjects, and good Chriſtians.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The Prophet is the ſnare of a Fowler in all his ways</p>
               <bibl>Hoſea 9.8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1661.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35730:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35730:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:35730:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35730:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He eye of the world hath now twice made his progreſs through all his 365 degrees, and you having received of the Pariſhioners of
<hi>Barham,</hi> ſince you came hither, well nigh ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pounds as there are degrees for his orb to move in, during all which we a conſiderable number of the ſame Pariſh, having with no ordinary pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence, as we (and others too) conceive, expected that you ſhould adminiſter the holy and ſaving Ordinances of our moſt bleſſed Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> amongſt us; but to our wonderment, and greif, finding ſo great (we will not yet ſay wilful) neglect in you therein, do now, (not out of any humour of oppoſition, or cavelling with you, qualities which become not the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of our Lord and Maſter, who is the <pb n="2" facs="tcp:35730:4"/>Prince of peace) but out of a ſincere and hearty affection to the glory of Almighty <hi>God,</hi> and the welfare of our ſouls, in all hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lity and meekneſs of Spirit, earneſtly deſire, &amp; implore you, from the very bottom of our hearts, as you are a Miniſter of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp; if as truly ſent amongſt us, as never choſen by us or liked of us, that you will not defraud us of that which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive belongs to us &amp; our Children, &amp; is no leſs then the holy <hi>Sacraments</hi> ordained by the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> himſelf till the time of his ſecond c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing.</p>
            <p>In this manifeſtation of our thoughts and deſires, you cannot expect from us plain Countrey-men, any Rhetorical floriſhes, any depth of humane learning, any wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſuch as is that of the world; theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, as they are above the ſphaere of our capacities, ſo are they far beneath the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel of our deſires; for we ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs we covet not the excellency of enticing words, or of the wiſdome of the men, or Princes of the world, but that which we daily and hourly beg for, is, that we may receive the Spirit of God, thereby to know Chriſt crucified and ſeaſonably to apply his merits to our ſouls, by participation of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35730:4"/>him in his holy <hi>Sacraments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We know that the world knew not <hi>God,</hi> in the wiſdome of
<hi>God,</hi> &amp; that natural man perceiveth not, nor indeed can he perceive the things of the Spirit of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We alſo know that not many wiſe men, not many mighty, not many noble, no not many Princes of the world hath <hi>God</hi> cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to be his favourites, but that he hath made choiſe of the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and the weak things of the world to confound the mighty, and the vile things of the world, and things which are deſpiſed, and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are: amongſt which fooliſh and weak things, we ranck our ſelves, neither having attained to, nor indeed much affected the wiſdome of the world, or excellency of words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> he knows, our meaning is honeſt, and very plain, and we ſhall ſincerely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our very hearts and thoughts to you.</p>
            <p>We truly confeſs, we ſpeak
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to your honor, we have not obſerved any of thoſe vices of drunkenneſs or prodigallity in you, which too too much abound in ſome men, &amp; we do as cordially wiſh, that ſpiritual <pb n="4" facs="tcp:35730:5"/>pride, ſecret malice, and immoderate covetouſneſs, (affections which many times are too too predominant in the Saints themſelves) may not take up any lodging in the chambers of your (as we hope) ſanctified heart: yet we muſt really tell you, we cannot but wounder with what face, with what reaſon, with what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience you could impoſe, or ſuffer your ſelf to be impoſed upon a people, which it ſhould ſeem you eſteem to be no better then Infidels, or dogs; for upon what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ground, we are to ſeek, why you ſhould refuſe to give that which is holy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us? we have not as yet denyed to give you temporal things, the fruits of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of our hands, the ſweat of our browes, the iſſue of our brains; why ſhould you withold from us thoſe which are ſpiritual, why ſhould you keep back from us thoſe tokens which our <hi>Lord</hi> and
<hi>Maſter</hi> hath left for us? we beſeech you tell us, do you think it your whole duty to get up into the Pulpit, and there only preach unto us, and by vertue thereof to extort tythes from us? in ſober ſadneſs, is there nothing elſe in your opinion required of a Miniſter of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ?</hi> are there no ſigns and ſeals of <pb n="5" facs="tcp:35730:5"/>the Covenant of grace to be delivered by you to us? is it therefore you refuſe to do it, becauſe you may think there be ſome amongſt us, that have been railors, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, wantons, fornicators, adulterers or covetous perſons? why? though not guilty, we can ſay, (it is to be feared) ſuch were ſome of you! and if you be now waſhed, ſanctified, and juſtified in the name of the
<hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> and by the Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> who knoweth, but by the ſame ſpirit, we may be in the like manner, waſhed, ſanctified and juſtified, and if ſo, or deſire to be ſo, pardon us, if we impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune the ſeals of Grace, which may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to our future glory.</p>
            <p>But if you think us, like Turks, Jews and Heathen unworthy of them, tel us ſo: if not, why have you witheld them from us all this while? if you will not give them us, but neceſſitate us to ſeek for them elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, we then deſire you to ſet down your reaſons under your hand: in the mean while we demand of you, with what conſcience or honor you can refuſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore back to the poorer ſort amongſt us, out of that great income you receive, thoſe moneyes they have been forced to expend
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35730:6"/>upon other Miniſters, for doing that which we conceive, of right belonged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o you to do; we ſay great income, becauſe it is great in it ſelf, greater in reſpect of the very little content you give us: for when we ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly look upon you, and behold you like <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> to have two faces, with the one looking earneſtly toward our Tithes without any regard to the Sacraments, with the other toward Womens weuld, we cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend you to be other then ſome ſtrange Miniſter, (we will not ſay Monſter) ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in amongſt us, and indeed ſuch an one, as neither we, nor our Fore-fathers ever ſaw in
<hi>Barham</hi> before.</p>
            <p>None of your Predeceſſors, ſome of whom, without all peradventure were pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and learned men,
<note place="margin">Hooker</note> ever, like unto your ſelf, denyed the <hi>Sacraments</hi> unto us: they knew them to ſerve as bonds of obedience to <hi>God,</hi> ſtrict obligations to the mutual exerciſe of Chriſtian Charity, provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to godlineſs, preſervations from ſin, memorials of the principal benefits of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> annexed for ever unto the new Teſtament, as other Rites were before with the Old; they knew them to be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants for the more ſecurity of our belief, <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35730:6"/>marks of diſtinction to ſeperate <hi>Gods</hi> own from ſtrangers: heavenly Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies ſanctified by God himſelf, and ordained to be adminiſtred in his <hi>Church</hi> as ſigns to know whereby <hi>God</hi> doth impart the vital or ſaving grace of <hi>Chriſt</hi> unto all that are capable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and as means which <hi>God</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in them unto whom he imparteth Grace. For ſith <hi>God</hi> in himſelf is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, and cannot by us be diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rned working, therefore when it ſeemeth good in the eyes of his heavenly wiſdome, that men for ſome ſpecial intent and purpoſe ſhould take notice of his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſence, he giveth them ſome plain, and ſenſible token, whereby to know what they cannot ſee. For <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſee
<hi>God</hi> was impoſible; yet
<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> by fire knew where the glory of <hi>God</hi> extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily was preſent. The
<note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 5 4.</note> Angel by whom
<hi>God</hi> endued the waters of the Pool called <hi>Betheſda</hi> with ſupernatural vertue to heal, was not ſeen of any, yet the time of the Angels preſence known by the troubled motions of the waters themſelves. The Apoſtles
<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 2.3.</note> by fiery tongues, which they ſaw, were admoniſhed when the Spirit <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35730:7"/>which they could not behold was upon them. In like manner it is with us;
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his holy Spirit, with all the bleſſed ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, though entring into the ſoul of man, we are not able to apprehend, or expreſs how, do notwithſtanding give notice of the times when they uſe to make their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, becauſe it pleaſeth Almighty <hi>God</hi> to communicate by ſenſible means thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which are incomprehenſible. Our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor knew the neceſſity of receiving the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> that grace is a conſequent of them, a thing which accompanieth them as their end, that it is not <hi>Gods</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary will to beſtow the grace of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> on any, but by the
<hi>Sacraments,</hi> which grace alſo they that receive by
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> or with <hi>Sacraments,</hi> receive it from him, and not from them; they knew that ſaving grace which <hi>Chriſt</hi> ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally is, or hath for the general good of the whole <hi>Church,</hi> he ſeverally deriveth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> every member thereof by <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and that they ſerve as the Inſtruments of
<hi>God</hi> to that end and purpoſe,
<note place="margin">Hooker</note> moral inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the uſe whereof is in our hands, the effect in his; they knew that for the uſe of them we have his expreſs commandment <pb n="9" facs="tcp:35730:7"/>for the effect, his promiſe; ſo that without our obedience to the one, there is of the other no apparant aſſurance, and we are not to doubt but that they really give what they promiſe, and are what they ſignifie; they knew that the
<hi>Sacraments</hi> are not bare reſemblances, or memorials of things abſent, or naked ſigns and Teſtimonies, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring us of grace received bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, but (as they are indeed and in verity) means effectual, whereby <hi>God</hi> when we take the
<hi>Sacraments</hi> delivereth into our hands that grace available unto eternal life, which grace, the <hi>Sacraments</hi> ſignifie or repreſent: and are they ſuch effectual means? are they neceſſary to ſalvation? are they by
<hi>God</hi> himſelf for ever annexed unto the new Teſtament? how great then is the neglect? how great the Offence? how deteſtable the wilfulneſs of thoſe men, who though im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred, ſet apart in a great meaſure for that purpoſe, and required by <hi>God</hi> himſelf to communicate them, in order to the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his people, ſhall notwithſtanding be careleſs in performance of his will, yea peremptorily deny to put his moſt ſacred and ſaving Ordinances in execution?</p>
            <p>Hath the great <hi>Judg</hi> of all the world ſaid,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35730:8"/>that
<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 3.33.</note> unleſs a man be born of water &amp; the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of heaven, &amp; except you eat of the
<note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 6.53.</note> fleſh of the
<hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> and drink his blood ye have no life in you; and hath the mirror of piety, and Learning affirmed, that we may with conſent of the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſtian world,
<note place="margin">Hooker</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of Baptiſm, and the Supper of the <hi>Lord</hi> to be neceſſary, the one to initiate, or begin, the other to conſummate, and make perfect our life in
<hi>Chriſt;</hi> who then can imagine otherwiſe? but great muſt be the ignorance or obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy of thoſe kind of men, who deny the adminiſtration of thoſe heavenly <hi>Myſteries</hi> which are ſo neceſſary to eternal life.</p>
            <p>For as concerning the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of Baptiſm, in the firſt place, we believe as we are not naturally men without birth, ſo neither are we Chriſtian men in the eye of the <hi>Church</hi> of
<hi>God,</hi> but by new birth, nor according to the manifeſt ordinary courſe of divine diſpenſation new born, but by that Baptiſm which both declareth and maketh us <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> In which reſpect we juſtly hold it to be the door of our actual entrance into <hi>Gods</hi> houſe, the firſt apparant begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, a ſeal perhaps to the grace of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35730:8"/>before received, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to our ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication here, a ſtep which hath not any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it.</p>
            <p>The Law of <hi>Christ</hi> tyeth all men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this baptiſm, expreſly ſpecified by water and the Spirit; water, as duty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired on our parts; the Spirit as a gift <hi>God</hi> beſtoweth; for unleſs as the Spirit is a neceſſary inward cauſe, ſo water were a neceſſary outward means to our regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; what conſtruction ſhould we give unto thoſe words to be new born, and that
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, even of water? why are we taught
<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 5.2.</note> that with water
<hi>God</hi> doth purifie and cleanſe his Church? wherefore do the Apoſtles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> term baptiſm
<note n="b" place="margin">Tit. 3.5.</note> a bath of Regeneration? what purpoſe had they in giving men advice to
<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 2.38.</note> receive outward bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and in perſwading them it did avail to remiſſion of ſins? If then <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf who giveth ſalvation, do require baptiſm, it is our duty who look for ſalvation, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to do that which is required, and religiouſly to feare the danger which may grow by the want thereof, and it behoov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all Miniſters of the Goſpel of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who have any fear of <hi>God</hi> in their hearts, and care of delivering mens ſouls <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35730:9"/>from ſin, to teach men the neceſſity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, &amp; not omit (when ocaſion is offered) this their neceſſary duty in their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. For though we grant that thoſe ſentences which make <hi>Sacraments</hi> moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to eternal life, are no prejudice to their ſalvation that want them by ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable neceſſity, and without any fault of their own, yet we ſay it ought in reaſon to be acknowledged likewiſe, that for as much as the
<hi>Lord</hi> himſelf maketh Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm neceſſary; neceſſary, whether we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the good received by it, or the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony yeilded unto
<hi>God</hi> of that humility and meek obedience, which repoſing who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſelf on the abſolute authority of his commandment, and on the truth of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly promiſe, doubteth not but from creatures deſpicable in their own condition and ſubſtance, to obtain grace of ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble value, or rather not from them, but from him, yet by them, as by his appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted means: and howſoever he, by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret wayes of his own incomprehenſible mercy, may be thought to ſave without Baptiſm, this cleareth not the <hi>Church</hi> from guiltineſs of blood, if through her ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous ſcrupuloſitie, lets, and impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <pb n="13" facs="tcp:35730:9"/>of leſs regard, ſhould cauſe a grace of ſo great moment to be witheld, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our mercileſs ſtrictneſs may be our own harm, although not theirs towards whom we ſhew it; and we for the hardneſs of our hearts may periſh, albeit they through
<hi>Gods</hi> unſpeakable mercy may live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> which did not afflict that innocent, whoſe circumciſion <hi>Moſes</hi> had overlong deferred, was about to have killed
<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf for the injury, which was done, through ſo great neglect, giving us thereby to underſtand, that they whom <hi>Gods</hi> own mercy ſaveth without us, are on our parts notwithſtanding, and as much as in us ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, even deſtroyed, when under unſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient pretences, we defraud them of ſuch ordinary outward helps as we ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit. Not that we hereby make Baptiſm a cauſe of grace, but ſay that the grace wh<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is given with baptiſm, doth ſo far forth depend on the outward <hi>Sacrament,</hi> that
<hi>God</hi> will have it embraced not only as a ſign or token what we receive, but alſo as an inſtrument or mean whereby we receive Grace.</p>
            <p>And as concerning the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> we ſay, that he which <pb n="14" facs="tcp:35730:10"/>hath ſaid of the one
<hi>Sacrament, waſh and be clean;</hi> hath ſaid concerning the other,
<hi>Eate and live.</hi> Life being therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed unto all men as their end, they which by Baptiſm have laid their foundation, and attained the firſt beginning of a new life, have here their nouriſhment and food, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for the continuance of life in them. Such as will live the life of God, muſt eat the fleſh, and drink the blood of the Son of man; becauſe this is a part of that diet, which if we want, we cannot live: whereas therefore in our infancy we are incorporated into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and by Baptiſme receive the grace of his Spirit, without any ſence or feeling of the gift which God beſtoweth, in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> we ſo receive the gift of God, that we know by grace, what the grace is which God giveth us, the decrees of our increaſe in holineſs and vertue, we ſee and can judge of them, we underſtand that the ſtrength of our life, began in
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that his fleſh is meat, and his blood is drink; not by ſurmized imagination, but truly, even ſo-truly, that through Faith we perceive in the ſigns of the Body and Blood Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally preſented, the very taſte of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal <pb n="15" facs="tcp:35730:10"/>Life: The grace of the <hi>Sacrament</hi> is here as the food which we eat and drink. The
<hi>Sacrament</hi> is a true and real partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who thereby imparteth himſelf, even his whole intire perſon as a myſtical head, into every ſoul that receiveth him; and every ſuch receiver doth thereby incorporate or unite himſelf unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as a Myſtical member of him, yea, of them alſo whom he acknowledgeth to be his own. And to whom the perſon of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is thus communicated, to them he giveth by the ſame <hi>Sacrament</hi> his Holy <hi>Spirit</hi> to ſanctifie them, as it ſanctifieth him which is their head; and what merit, force, or vertue ſoever there is in his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed body and bloud, we freely, fully and wholy have it by this <hi>Sacrament;</hi> the effect whereof in us is a real tranſmutation of our Souls and Bodies from ſin to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, from death and corruption, to immortality and life; and though the
<hi>Sacrament</hi> it ſelf be but a corruptible and earthly creature, yet he by the ſtrength of his glorious power, will bring to paſs that the Bread and Cup which he giveth us, ſhall be truly the thing he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:35730:11"/>This <hi>Sacrament</hi> keepeth
<hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in a continual remembrance of that propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory ſacrifice, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> once for all offered by his death upon the Croſs, to reconcile us to God: He was himſelf once really offered, and as oft as this <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> is celebrated, ſo oft is he ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally offered by the faithfull. This <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> confirmeth our Faith; for God by it doth ſignifie and ſeal unto us from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that according to the promiſe and new Covenant which he hath made in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he will truly receive into his grace and mercy all penitent believers who duly receive this holy <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and that for the merit of the death and paſſion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he will as verily forgive them all their ſins, as they are made partakers of this <hi>Sacrament.</hi> It is alſo a pledg, and Symbole of the moſt neer and effectual communion which Chriſtians have with their Head, from which communion there followeth to the faithfull, many ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable benefits, as his taking by impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation all their ſins and guiltineſs upon him, to ſatisfie Gods juſtice for them; and he freely gives by imputation unto us all his righteouſneſs in this life, and all his right <pb n="17" facs="tcp:35730:11"/>unto eternal life, when this is ended; and counteth all the good, or ill that is done unto us, as done to his own perſon: there likewiſe floweth from <hi>Chriſt</hi> nature into our nature united unto him, the lively ſpirit, and breath of Grace, which reneweth us unto a ſpiritual life, and ſo ſanctifieth our minds, wills, and affections, that we day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grow more and more conformable to the Image of
<hi>Chriſt;</hi> he alſo beſtoweth upon us all ſaving graces neceſſary to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain eternal life, as the ſence of <hi>Gods</hi> love, the aſſurance of our election, with regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſanctification, and grace to do good works. This <hi>Sacrament</hi> alſo feeds the Souls of the faithfull in the aſſured hope of life everlaſting, and withal doth ſeal unto them the aſſurance of the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that life. <hi>Manna,</hi> Angels food, fed the Iſraelites forty years in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but behold a better food is prepared for them, even the body, and blood of our moſt bleſſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> the bread of life, on which whoſoever by a ſincere and ſtedfaſt faith do feed, it will nouriſh their ſouls for ever unto a bleſſed life without end: in order to which, it is an aſſured pledg of the ſpiritual reſurrection of our <pb n="18" facs="tcp:35730:12"/>ſouls from the death of ſin here, and of the corporal reſurrection of our bodies at the laſt day; of the firſt reſurrection our <hi>Saviour</hi> hath ſaid,
<note n="a" place="margin">John 6.57.</note> 
               <hi>He that eateth me even he ſhall live by me;;</hi> of the ſecond <hi>He</hi> himſelf hath alſo ſaid,
<note n="b" place="margin">57.</note> 
               <hi>He that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood, hath eternal life, and I will raiſe him at the laſt day:</hi> for this <hi>Sacrament</hi> ſignifieth and ſealeth unto us, that
<hi>Chriſt</hi> died, and roſe again for us, and that <hi>His</hi> fleſh quickeneth and nouriſheth unto eternal life, and that therefore our bodies ſhall ſurely be then raiſed unto that life; for ſeeing our
<hi>Head</hi> is riſen, all the members of the body ſhall likewiſe ſurely riſe again, for how can thoſe bodies fed and nouriſhed with the body and blood of the Lord of life, but be raiſed up with him again at that day unto life? it being given by <hi>Him</hi> for their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſalvation.</p>
            <p>It was neither Saint nor Angel, but the Son of <hi>God</hi> himſelf who ordained this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and is the chiefeſt memorial left by <hi>Him</hi> of our Redemption; our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, which was the chiefeſt benefit that ever man needed from <hi>God,</hi> or that <hi>God</hi> ever beſtowed up on man; and there <pb n="19" facs="tcp:35730:12"/>fore every Chriſtian ſhould account this holy ſupper the chiefeſt and moſt joyful feaſt in this world, and come unto it with praiſe and thankſgiving: the ſinner laying aſide his ſins muſt come to this feaſt, the envious man his enmitie and come; he that hath variety of ſecular imployments muſt lay aſide his ſecular imployments and and come and converſe with
<hi>God.</hi> He that is well grounded in grace muſt come, becauſe he is excellently diſpoſed to ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a feaſt, but he that is but in the infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his piety, had need to come, that ſo he may grow in grace; the ſtrong muſt come, leaſt they become weak, and the weak, that they may become ſtrong; the ſick muſt come to be cured, the healthful to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: they that have leaſure muſt come becauſe they have no excuſe; they that have no leaſure muſt come hither, that by ſo excellent Religion they may ſanctifie their buſineſs: The penitent ſinners muſt come, that they may be juſtified; and they that are juſtified, that they may be juſtified ſtill; they that have fears and great reverence to theſe myſteries, and think no preparation to be ſufficient, muſt receive, that they may learn to receive
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35730:13"/>the more worthily, and they that have a leſs degree of reverence, muſt come often, to have it hightned: Here are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies for all ſick and ſorrowful ſinners, the very letter of the word of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> giveth plain ſecurity that theſe <hi>myſteries</hi> do as nails faſten us unto his very Croſs, that by him we draw out as touching efficacy, force and vertue, even the blood of his gored ſide, in the wounds of out <hi>Redeemer,</hi> we there dip our tongues, we are dyed red both within and without, our hunger is ſatisfied and our thirſt for ever quenched; they are things wonderful which he feeleth, great which he ſeeth, and unheard of which he uttereth, whoſe ſouls is poſſeſt of this Paſchal Lamb, and made joyful in the ſtrength of this new wine; this Bread hath in it more then the ſubſtance which our eyes behold, this Cup hallowed with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn benediction, availeth to the endleſs life and welfare both of ſoul and body, in that it ſerveth as well for a medicine to heal our infirmities and purge our ſins, as for a ſacrifice of thanksgiving, which tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, it ſanctifieth, it enlightneth with belief, it truly conformeth us unto the Image of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who by vertue of <pb n="21" facs="tcp:35730:13"/>his divine benediction, with hands and eyes lifted up to heaven, firſt bleſſed, and conſecrated thoſe choſen elements of bread &amp; wine, &amp; made them for ever inſtruments of life, for the endleſs good of all genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: O how inexpreſſibly comfortable are the benefits devolved upon us hereby! O how infinite are the joyes, ſuch as eye hath not ſeen nor eare heard, nor can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the heart of man prepared for the worthy receivers! to ſuch belongs life, life indeed, life everlaſting; with thoſe is the Tabernacle of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> himſelf ſhall be their <hi>God,</hi> and He will wipe away all tears from their eyes, no more death, no more ſorrow, no more crying, no more pain ſhall trouble them: He that is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the beginning and the end will be their <hi>God,</hi> and they ſhall be his Sons, they ſhall inhabit the great City, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Jeruſalem enlightned with the glory of <hi>God,</hi> and walled with a great and high wall, founded upon twelve foundations, garniſhed with all manner of precious ſtones, and the names of the Lambs twelve Apoſtles; the gates belonging to this City being no leſs in number then twelve, and every one of them made of <pb n="22" facs="tcp:35730:14"/>Pearl,
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.21</note> and the pavement of it of pure Gold; a City having no need of Sun or Moon to ſhine in it, having the glory of God to light it, and the law to be the light of it; to this City all the Kings of the Earth ſhall bring honor and glory, and all thoſe who religiouſly hunger and thurſt after the body and blood of this
<hi>Lamb,</hi> and worthily partake of it, ſhall walk in the light of it: And ſhall any hunger and thirſt after this ſoul-ſaving heavenly ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet? Shall ſome be ſet apart on purpoſe, by an Almighty, gracious and liberal inviter freely to deliver it unto them? And are all theſe mentioned benefits and priviledges, yea, Heaven it ſelf promiſed to them that hunger and thirſt, and partake of it? and yet ſhall there be any who will not only wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully neglect, but alſo peremptorily deny to miniſter at this holy feaſt, and thereby ſuffer the hunger and thirſt of poor ſouls to remain unſatisfyed? Shall any in like manner whom our moſt mercifull <hi>Saviour Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath commanded to <hi>Suffer little children to come unto him, for to ſuch belongs the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> be ſo wickedly hard-hearted, ſo maliciouſly bent, ſo without all natural compaſſion,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35730:14"/>as to ſhut the door againſt thoſe poor little infants, deny them a little water Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally to waſh away their ſins with; keep back from them the ſign and ſeal of <hi>Gods</hi> promiſe, and as much as in them lieth put them out of the Covenant of Grace, and thruſt them into the wofull pit of everlaſting Perdition? Certainly, if we had not ſeen ſuch creatures with our eyes, wee ſhould hardly have believed our ears at any mens mentioning of them; ſuch there are amongſt us, and our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren after us will declare the mighty work of diviſion they have wrought in our days; which they firſt prepared under colour of Religion, to accompliſh their own crooked ends thereby. And theſe people do ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate themſelves from others, deſiring to be thought more holy then they. Theſe the Apoſtles long ſince foretold ſhould come to deceive in the latter times; they have thruſt out pious and learned men out of their ſeats, and exalted Dunces, and themſelves in the room of them; they have cauſed Schiſmes and Hereſies amongſt the people, which happen by reaſon of our ſins, through the juſt judgment of our <hi>God,</hi> wherewith from on high he hath <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35730:15"/>viſited us, by permitting thoſe falſe lights to ſhine in theſe times of darkneſs, to lead our feet out of the way of peace, and deny us the Holy <hi>Sacraments,</hi> which were ordeined for the remiſſion of our ſins: ſuch ſtrange lights there are now; and what makes them ſuch? Semblably it is to be feared, ignorant obſtinacy, and ſelf-ſeeking ends; for who can imagine it to be other then ignorant obſtinacy in theſe crabbed Doctors, who alledge no other then unſatisfactory reaſons, for their omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of holy and neceſſary duties; as becauſe forſooth the people (whom they expect ſhould do juſt as they would have them, be it right or wrong) will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently go out of the old, and inſtantly come into a new Church way; and that even before they are ſhewn what it is, or where it lies, or the contrivers of it, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have thorowly agreed what it ſhall be; a way which when by themſelves (as they may think) perfected, will in all likelyhood be as little liked of, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the moſt godly, moſt wiſe, and moſt learned men of this Nation, as it hath been practiſed by them, ſince the time of our bleſſed <hi>Saviors</hi> coming into <pb n="25" facs="tcp:35730:15"/>the world, till the firſt year of <hi>Liberty,</hi> for every one to take upon him what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion he pleaſeth, broach what Hereſie he fancieth, and be of what Sect he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth moſt to his own advantage.</p>
            <p>And is it any other then an unſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory reaſon in thoſe Auſtere Doctors, which will not adminiſter the holy <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of Baptiſm to thoſe children, whoſe Parents though viſibly in the Covenant of <hi>God,</hi> and viſible members of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Church, though they acknowledg them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to believe in him, and by vertue of his merits to obtain everlaſting life; and though they deſire to partake of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, yet becauſe they will not in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing dance after their pipe, will not have a hand with them in renting in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the ſeamleſs Coat of their <hi>Saviour,</hi> will not apprehend all their errors to be truths, will not ſuffer themſelves to be rid upon by theſe unmercifull horſmen, under pretence of Church diſcipline, will not break the bond of unity amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but maintain a ſociable familiarity, and ſometimes as they have too too much cauſe, ſpeak againſt Phariſaical practiſes, yet becauſe they will not confeſs all that <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35730:16"/>theſe teachers ſay to be true, all that they practiſe to be good, all that they would have done to be of abſolute neceſſity to be done, ſhall therefore be denied the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Holy <hi>Sacraments,</hi> though accuſed by no other then themſelves to be ignorant, ſcandalous and ſcoffers at Religion, and hereupon be rejected as Children of wrath, plain Aliens, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without hope, utterly without God in this preſent world.
<hi>Miſerable were the condition of man, if it were by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Law eſtabliſhed, that theſe partial and hard-hearted Rulers ſhould be his Accuſers and Judges.</hi> For ſhould not God through his unſpeakeable goodneſs, ſhew mercy unto thouſands of poor Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whoſe remote forefathers loved him? They muſt forever go without it for theſe men, and all becauſe their immediate parents were ſuch as would not every way ſquare themſelves according to their wild fancies, and unrectified judgments. But ſuppoſe thoſe immediate parents were wicked indeed, as they many times only pretend them to be ſo: Hath not God told them plain enough by the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ez. 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>That the child ſhall not ſuffer for <pb n="27" facs="tcp:35730:16"/>the iniquity of the Father?</hi> &amp; is it not evident that the Children of wicked Parents a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Jews were circumciſed? and if ſo, why may not Children proceeding from the like Parents of the Chriſtians be baptized, ſith (it is not to be doubted) his hand is not ſhortned, and he hath given as large priviledges to us under the Goſpel, as he gave to them under the Law: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we ſhould be looſers by the coming of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which <hi>Credat Judaeus Apella, non nos,</hi> though the circumciſed Jew will believe, we will be far from giving credit to any ſuch monſtruous improbability
<note place="margin">Niſi forte arbitramur Chriſtum in ſuo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventu. Patris gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>am im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minuiſſe aut decur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe, quod ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia non va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. Inſt. lib. 4. c. 16. ſect. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We read that Saint <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt ſprang for joy in his Mothers womb, at the ſalutation of the Virgin, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.41. but are to ſeek for the cauſe of ſo great joy, had his birth been ſo diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to him, and others in that condition; the coming of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> witneſs the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of an Angel from heaven, and the Holy Ghoſt bearing witneſs of the truth of that Teſtimony, was
<hi>joyous</hi> to all:
<note place="margin">Lu. 2.20.</note> all ſexes, all conditions, all ages, advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to all, even to Infants. Our moſt bleſſed
<hi>Saviour</hi> brought grace along with him: Grace and Truth ſaith
<hi>John</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 1.17.</note> came <pb n="28" facs="tcp:35730:17"/>by (&amp; with) <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> Grace in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative degree reaching &amp; ſpreading far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under the new, then the old Teſtament. The grace of <hi>God</hi> which bringeth ſalvation hath appeared, ſaith the
<hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> to all men <hi>i.e.</hi> to all ſorts of ages &amp; conditions of men. The grace of <hi>God</hi> in an ordinary diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was firſt appropriated to the Jews, they were then his favourites, to whom his grace in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was manifeſted; but now that grace hath appeared to all men; the grace of the Goſpel is more ample; and every wayes greater Grace then that before, or under the Law:
<hi>God</hi> having provided ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things for us (ſaith the Apoſtle)
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.40</note> more, greater, and better privileges for us under the Goſpel, then for them under the Law; and by conſequence for the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Chriſtians, then for the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Jews, which could not be, if our Children had not right to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as well as theirs. Had theſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers who are thus ſcrupulous in admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring this holy Ordinance, peruſed and minded holy and learned
<hi>Perkins</hi> his works, as much as they uſe to read, and and ſtudy the noval and ſchiſmatical Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets of the time, they might have been
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35730:17"/>taught by him that <hi>The Children of Parents that are profeſſed members of the Church, (though cut off for a time, upon ſome offence committed) have right to Baptiſm, becauſe it is not in the power of man to cut them off from Chriſt though excommunicated;</hi> which being ſo, why may not the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren deſcending from Parents (though in their perſons wicked) not excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, have right to the ſacred Ordinance of Baptiſm, ſith thoſe of the very excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated (in the Judgment of ſo profound a Maſter as <hi>Perkins</hi>) have right thereunto.</p>
            <p>But behold the opinion by the practice of a greater then
<hi>Perkins,</hi> even of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt himſelf, who baptized all that came unto him for his Baptiſm, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.5. amongſt others even thoſe very <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces,</hi> whom at the ſame time he called a generation of vipers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.7. and the latter of whom denyed the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And as they are no other then unſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory reaſons, which are given for not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring the holy Sacrament of Baptiſm, what are they better which are rendred for their not admitting thoſe that are Religious and knowing Chriſtians to the ſupper of <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35730:18"/>the Lord, becauſe peradventure there may be ſome in a Pariſh who may be Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous or ignorant; or others who will refuſe to make anſwer to ſome needleſs queſtions may be demanded by ſuch as rake it to be a part of their function, to make a deeper ſearch into conſciences, then any Law of
<hi>God</hi> or reaſon of man inforceth, and upon this denyal they ſhall be put off to another time, from the myſtery of heavenly grace, though for piety, and knowledge they be ſufficiently capable: in like manner others who deny not to ſubmit themſelves to this ſevere inquiſition, yet if they be perſons any way diſtaſted by them, if theſe do not make anſwer
<hi>iiſàem terminis</hi> to that they would have them, though in effect knowingly enough, they ſhall notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be put off to farther tryal; in which men, although there ſhould be found ſome weakneſs indeed, (as it is too too often only pretended there is,) yet ſhould they in divers conſiderations be cheriſhed, according to the merciful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and precepts, whereby the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath taught us, towards ſuch to ſhew compaſſion, to receive them with lenity and all meekneſs; if any thing be <pb n="31" facs="tcp:35730:18"/>ſhaken in them, to ſtrengthen it, not to quench with delayes &amp; jealouſies that fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſmoak of godlineſs which ſeemeth to breath from them, but to build whereſoever there is any foundation, and to add per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection unto ſlender beginnings, and that, as by other offices of piety, ſo by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which <hi>Christ</hi> hath left in his Church, not only for preſervation of ſtrength, but alſo for relief of weakneſs.</p>
            <p>Far differrent from theſe men was the practice of the Church of
<hi>Corinth,</hi> unto which (it ſeems) many came over from Heatheniſm, and as many as came in unto them, all were admitted to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, amongſt whom ſome were ſuch lukewarme Chriſtians, that they were ſometimes ready to go to their Idols, and ſometimes to Church (to ſay nothing of thoſe Corinthians who were (as it is to be doubted)
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.20.</note> given to ſtrife, envying, wrath, contentions, backbiting whiſperings, pride, and diſcord:
<note place="margin">v. 21.</note> and others of them who were given to uncleanneſs, fornication, and wantonneſs,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 15.12.</note> and other ſome who were ſo ſcrupulous as to make a doubt of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection it ſelf)
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.18,21.</note> yet theſe Idolatrous Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians whom we ſhall alſo find muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, <pb n="32" facs="tcp:35730:19"/>and even drunken together at this Table, whilſt they are but willing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are admitted with the reſt to the
<hi>Sacrament</hi> True it is, they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved (as they juſtly deſerved to be ſo) for their prophanation, and directed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, and carry themſelves better for the future, but as for their coming together, and general participation, that was but their duty, and nothing ſaid againſt it.</p>
            <p>And this general participation of the Corinthians appears plainly by the ſence of the words of the Apoſtle to them,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.5.</note> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, that all the Iſraelites that paſſed thorow the Sea, and wilderneſs, were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to both Sacraments as well as they, even thoſe very ſcandalous ones, with whom <hi>God</hi> was not well pleaſed, but like to them deſtroyed in the wilderneſs, yet it was a juſt puniſhment upon them, when they ran to Idols, as they in like manner did, and therefore bid them take heed, and not think that they ſhould eſcape <hi>Gods</hi> judgments, if they walked not anſwerable to their profeſſion, notwithſtanding their admittance to the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>And this is not only evident by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Corinthians and Iſraelites, <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35730:19"/>but by that notable one of our bleſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> himſelf, who admitted even <hi>Judas</hi> that Arch-Traytor to the Paſſover, if not to his ſupper, (however it is the ſame in ſignification) ſo that thoſe who will not be otherwiſe moved to a more free admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> then is of late dayes allowed of, might very well be enduced to do it, if not by what the Corinthians and Iſraelites did, yet by the example of the Son of <hi>God</hi> himſelf; unleſs they will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhut their eyes againſt that light which came into the world to illuminate all thoſe who have a deſire to ſee the right way, and walk in it.</p>
            <p>And that ſome with-hold the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> from thoſe they ought to miniſter them to, may it not be doubted they do it out of ſelfiſh ends? which if well looked into, will prove the ſtate of many queſtions which go under the notion of Religion in theſe dayes, as well as it hath in the times of old: hence it is that they account they ſhall be the more ſought unto, the more held in reverence, the more engrandize their power, and hold men in obedience and ſlavery under them, and they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be in ſubjection to none; this ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſhneſs,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35730:20"/>if thorowly ſearcht into, will be found ſecretly to contain that poyſon which hath ſo powerfully wrought upon the braines of ſo many Presbyterians and other Sectaries, and cauſed them to caſt ſo many ſtumbling blocks in the way, and ſet ſo many fences between the people and the body of their Saviour: (miſtake us not we beſeech you, we mean not all, but ſome of your profeſſion:) hence is it that ſo many heart burnings, ſo many contentions, ſo many diviſions hath happened between Church-men and Church-men, as well as between them and the people: however in this particular, as <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> though they differed otherwiſe, yet agreed againſt <hi>Chriſt;</hi> ſo in this, too too many of each ſect joyn hand in hand in ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to give the bread of life to poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which might nouriſh and comfort their hungry ſouls unto life everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</p>
            <p>But we hear you ſay, If we will come under a Presbyterial Diſcipline, you will adminiſter the Sacraments to us, otherwiſe not.</p>
            <p>To this we demand of you, Would you have us to ſubject our ſelves to a diſcipline <pb n="35" facs="tcp:35730:20"/>againſt our conſciences, a diſcipline not eſtabliſhed by Law, nor congruent to our Liberty? would you have us put our necks under the yoak of a diſcipline, which we truly conceive hath been the anvil upon which ſo many engines have been framed, which have ſo much battered down the quiet and peace both of Church and State?
<note place="margin">Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords and Commons to the Scots Commiſ. p. 49.</note> Have not the favourers of this diſcipline graſped at unlimited power, ſuch as neither deriveth its beginning, nor willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth its commands from the Magiſtrate? whom they would have countenance them in all their Actions, and yet not allow of his rules and direction; they would have him cenſure and condemn, or others by his Authority, which is all one, and yet will not allow him to know and judg: they will call for his hand to ſtrike, and yet not allow him an eye to ſee.</p>
            <p>Without offence, be it in a good hour ſpoken, we apprehend this diſcipline to be of all other moſt injurious to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, moſt oppreſſive to the Subject, and moſt pernitious to both: it is the very quinteſſence of refined Pouery, and a greater Tyranny then ever
<hi>Rome</hi> brought forth, inconſiſtent with all forms of Civil
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35730:21"/>government, deſtructive to all ſorts of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, a rack to the conſcience, the heavieſt preſſure that can fall upon a people, and ſo much the more dangerous, becauſe by the ſpecious pretence of divine Inſtitution, it takes away the ſight, but not the burden of ſlavery.</p>
            <p>How it is injurious to the Magiſtrate, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by that little hath been ſaid already; but will farther appear,
<list>
                  <item>1. By overthrowing his Rights in convocating Synods to order Eccleſiaſticall affaires, and reform the Church within his Dominions.</item>
                  <item>2. By robbing him of the laſt appeal of his Subjects.</item>
                  <item> 3. By exempting the Miniſters from due puniſhment.</item>
                  <item> 4. By ſubjecting the ſupream Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to their Cenſures, even to the higheſt Cenſure of excommunication, that very engine by which the Popes exalted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above Emperors.</item>
                  <item> 5. By robbing the Magiſtrate of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſative Power.</item>
                  <item> 6. By cheating him of his Civil Power in order to Religion.</item>
                  <item> 7. By challenging an exorbitant Power by Divine Right.</item>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:35730:21"/>
                  <item> 8. And by making a very Monſter of the Common-wealth.</item>
                  <item> 9. And little more then a Cypher of Parliaments.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All which are evidently demonſtrated, not by ſome extraordinary practiſes, juſtified only by the pretence of invincible neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (a weak patrociny for general Doctrine) nor by the ſingle opinions of ſome capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fellows, but by the Scottiſh book of Diſcipline, by the Acts of their general and provincial Aſſemblies, by the concurrent votes and writings of their Commiſſioners, as is exactly to be ſeen in the fair warning to take heed of this Diſcipline by <hi>Dr. Joh. Bromwel</hi> L. Biſhop of <hi>London-Derry</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> And how it is oppreſſive to particular perſons, and full of rigor, and like
<hi>Dracos</hi> laws that were written in blood, it will appear by inflicting Church cenſures upon ſlight grounds; as for an uncomely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, a vain word, for ſuſpition of Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Pride, for ſuperfluity of rayment ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for coſt or faſhion, for dancing at a wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or of ſervants in the ſtreets, for wearing a mans hair <hi>al a mode:</hi> They ſcarce allow a man a Latitude of diſcretion in any thing: all men, even their ſuperiors muſt be their <pb n="38" facs="tcp:35730:22"/>ſlaves, or pupils. If a man will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs himſelf a Delinquent, be ſorry for giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Presbyters any offence, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf in his hair, apparel, diet, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing, to what theſe rough-hewen <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to's</hi> ſhall preſcribe, they will proceed againſt him to excommunication.</p>
            <p>By this Diſcipline a man is puniſhed twice for the ſame crime; firſt by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, according to the Laws of God and the Land, for the offence; then by the Cenſures of the Church, for the ſcandal. To this agrees their Synod, nothing forbids the ſame fault in the ſame man to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one way by the Political power, another way by the Eccleſiaſtical;
<note place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>or. 63.</note> by that, under the formality of a crime with corporal or pecuniary puniſhment; by this, under the formality of ſcandal, with ſpiritual cenſures.</p>
            <p>Thus their Liturgy in expreſs terms, All crimes which by the Law of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves death, deſerves alſo excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Yea, though an offender abide an aſſiſe, and be abſolved by the ſame, yet may the Church enjoyn him publick ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. Or if the Magiſtrate ſhall not think fit in his Judgment, or cannot in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſcience proſecute the party upon the <pb n="39" facs="tcp:35730:22"/>Churches intimation, the Church may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh the Magiſtrate publickly. And if no remedy be found, excommunicate the offender, firſt, for his crime, and then for his being ſuſpected to have corrupted the Judg. By which we obſerve, how theſe ſevere Diſciplinarians bring all crimes whatſoever, great and ſmall, within their Juriſdiction; how that a Delinquents tryal for his life is no ſufficient ſatisfaction to them; and how that to ſatisfie their own humours, they care not how they blemiſh publickly the reputation of the Magiſtrate upon frivolous conjectures.</p>
            <p>And as they bring all crimes great and ſmall, ſo do they bring all degrees under their Juriſdiction. The ſupreme Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate ſhall be bearded and mated by every ordinary Presbyter; witneſs that inſolent ſpeech of Mr. <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> to King <hi>James,</hi> Sir, <hi>I</hi> ſee your reſolution is to take <hi>Huntley</hi> in favour; if you do, I will oppoſe: you ſhall chooſe whether you will loſe <hi>Huntley,</hi> or me, for us both you cannot keep. It is nothing with them for a pedant to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the ballance with the Prince, and moſt Potent Peer of the Realm. And as for the common people, they ſhall have <pb n="40" facs="tcp:35730:23"/>an high Commiſſion in every Pariſh, and groan under the Arbitrary Decrees of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant unexperienced Governors, who know no Law but their own wils, who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve no order but what they liſt: under theſe men, Parents ſhall loſe the free diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of their own Children in marriage:
<note place="margin">1 Book diſc. 9. head.</note> if the child deſire a husband or a wife, and the Parents gain-ſtand their requeſt, and have no other cauſe then the common of men have, to wit, lack of goods, or becauſe the other party is not of birth high enough, upon the childs deſire, the Miniſter is to travail with the Parents, &amp; if he find no juſt cauſe to the contrary, may admit them to the marriage: For the work of
<hi>God</hi> ought not to be hindred, by the corrupt affections of worldly men. This doctrine is very high, but their practice yet much more high; for the Presbyterians will compel the wronged Parent to give that child as great a portion as any of his other children.</p>
            <p>All Maſters and Miſtreſſes of families, of what age or condition ſoever, muſt come once a year before the Presbyter, with their houſhold, to be examined perſonally, whether they be fit to receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in reſpect of their knowledg and <pb n="41" facs="tcp:35730:23"/>otherwiſe; and if they ſuffer their children or ſervants to continue in wilful ignorance (though they cannot help it) they muſt undergo the ſeverity, and extreme rigor of their excommunication;
<note place="margin">1 Book diſc. 9 head.</note> after which ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, no perſon (his wife and family only excepted) may have any kind of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with him that is excommunicated, they may not eat with him, nor drink with him, nor buy with him, nor ſel to him; they may not ſalute him, nor ſpeak to him, except it be by licence of the Presbytery.
<note place="margin">1 Book diſc. 7. head.</note> His Children begotten &amp; born after that ſentence, and before his reconciliation to
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> may not be admitted to Baptiſm, until they be of age to require it, or the Mother, or ſome ſpecial friend, being a member of that Church, preſent the child, abhorring and damning the iniquity and obſtinate contempt of the Father. And all this being not enough, they proceed to an outlawing of the party, and a confiſcation of his goods, and putting him out of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates protection, ſo as any man may kill him and be unpuniſhed: yea the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty excommunicated is not ſo much as to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend or hear theſe fatal letters granted.</p>
            <p>And that the people may the more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently <pb n="42" facs="tcp:35730:24"/>ſuffer all this harſhneſs from them, may the more quietly indure all their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy oppreſſions, and the more humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves to all their rigid Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, they perſwade them, that they are bound in conſcience to hear and obey their voice, and reverence the Majeſty of the Son of God ſpeaking in them; for having made their Conſiſtories the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of Chriſt, they expect that their determinations ſhall paſs for the ſentences of Chriſt; and thus theſe proud Vicars having mounted themſelves aloft, they ſit upon the Temple of God, and exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above all that the Scripture calleth <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how can any man be ſo ignorant, ſo ſtupid, ſo void of reaſon, as to think that theſe men can be led by an infallible ſpirit, who in this manner, like the Lords of the Heathen, ſeek for Dominion and Power! who aim at Authority and Rule in this world, of which they cannot but know their Maſters Kingdome is not! who being puffed up with an unparallel'd pride have made themſelves drunk with the ſpirit of Antichriſt, and ſo drunk, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſtagger, and are in danger of falling
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35730:24"/>down even level with the the ground!</p>
            <p>But ſith they, the better to ſupport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from falling, have thought fit to joyn unto them a ſort of men whom they have Chriſtned by the name of lay Elders, and will have them looked upon as Commiſſioners of Chriſt; we will let you know, that we are not ignorant of the true reaſon of their annexing this conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction copulative unto them; for the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick projector and founder of this new diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, by name
<hi>Calvin</hi> (a man famous for his great wiſdome) the more ſurely and eaſily to bring that beaſt of many heads, the people, to aſſent &amp; contribute their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and endeavours towards the erecting of the building, whereof he had before hand conceived an <hi>Idea</hi> in his mind, thought good to tender an offer to them (plauſible enough in outward ſhew) that for every Miniſter, who ſhould ſit perpetual Judg, they ſhould annually chuſe two lay Elders out of every Pariſh amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and they to ſit with them in the ſtanding Eccleſiaſtical Court which was to be eſtabliſhed, to be Judges together with them in the ſame: and theſe two ſorts ſhould have a care of all mens manners, <pb n="44" facs="tcp:35730:25"/>power of determining all kind of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical cauſes, and Authority to convene, to controul, to puniſh, as far as with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, whomſoever they ſhould think worthy, none either ſmall or great excepted: now the people (who are ever taken and deluded with fair ſhews, (and to the worlds end will be ſo) rather then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alities,) conceiting this ods of two to one, to be ſufficient to remedy any inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence might ariſe by the Miniſtry, willingly enough embraced the Offer, and joyntly ſet to their helping hands and heads to bring the buſineſs to perfection; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, after no ſmall oppoſition which was made by the wiſer ſort, effected what they intended; we ſay, no ſmall oppoſition, for the more quick-ſighted, and men of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeſt judgment among the layty, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw that this filling up of the ſeates in the Conſiſtory with ſo great a number of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, was but to pleaſe the mind of the people, to the end they might think their own ſway ſomewhat; but when things came to tryal of practice, their Paſtors learning would be at all times of force to over-perſwade ſimple men, who knowing the time of their own Preſidentſhip to be <pb n="45" facs="tcp:35730:25"/>but ſhort, would alwayes ſtand in fear of their Miniſters perpetual Authority: and hereupon profeſſed with greater ſtomach their Judgments, that ſuch a diſcipline was little better then Popiſh Tyranny, diſguiſed and tendered unto them under a new form. But how much ſoever the more prudential men gainſaid this upſtart diſcipline, yet certain it is, in thoſe times of diſtraction (as the Citty of <hi>Geneva</hi> was then in) (as we have in like manner ſeen in theſe our dayes by woful experience)
<note place="margin">Anno Do. 1541.</note> not the wiſe, but the many, like a boiſterous torrent, beares down all before them, and to the diſturbance of the world, do what they liſt, ſo (they) eſtabliſhed this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline. A diſcipline which they peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily affirmed to have been taught by <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apoſtles in the Word of <hi>God;</hi> and yet full fifteen hundred years have paſſed from the birth of our Saviour till the ſetting up thereof, and they cannot, during all that time, ſhew us one Church upon the face of the whole earth which ever found out or erected it, till this preſent time: and now forſooth this diſcipline is become <hi>The Scepter of Chriſt, the eternal Goſpel:</hi> and where did this Scepter lie <pb n="46" facs="tcp:35730:26"/>hid during all theſe hundreds of years, that we cannot find out the leaſt foot-ſtep of it in the meaneſt village of Chriſtendome? This world draws toward an end: was this diſcipline fitted and contrived for the world to come? or how can it be the eternal Goſpel?</p>
            <p>We ſhould be injurious unto Charity it ſelf, if we ſhould affirm all theſe men who are of this ſtamp, to have wilfully gone out of this right way into this Labyrinth, and accordingly to have led others a long with them in a maze; or ſhould ſurmiſe all thoſe who have been miſguided, knowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to continue in an error; no, we have a better opinion of ſome of them, who no doubt have a conceit of the divinity of their diſcipline, and yet are truly godly men in their hearts, ſincere in their affections, upright in their meanings: but we ſay, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly godly men in all ages have erred, and without all peradventure ſo do the beſt of theſe; and that the founder hereof him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was but a man, we all know, we no leſs know men are but men, and <hi>humanum eſt errare:</hi> what moved him at firſt to fancy this diſcipline, and afterwards to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it, is to be ſeen at large in judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> his preface.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:35730:26"/>Nature worketh in us all a love to our own counſels. The contradiction of others is a fan to in flame that love. Our love ſet on fire to maintain that which once we have done, ſharpneth the wit to diſpute, to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, and by all means to reaſon for it: wherefore a marvel it were, if a man of ſo great capacity, having ſuch incitements to make him deſirous of all kind of furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances unto his cauſe, could eſpie in the whole Scripture of <hi>God,</hi> nothing which might breed, at the leaſt a probable opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of likelihood, that Divine Authority it ſelf was the ſame way ſomewhat inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And all which the wit, even of
<hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> was able from thence to draw, by ſif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the very utmoſt ſentence and ſillable, is no more, then that certain ſpeeches there are, which to him did ſeem to intimate, that all Chriſtian Churches ought to have their Elderſhips endued with power of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and that a part of thoſe Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips every where ſhould be choſen out from amongſt the Layty, after that form which himſelf had framed <hi>Geneva</hi> unto. But what argument can be ſhewn wherby it was ever prov'd by <hi>Calvin,</hi> that any one ſentence of Scripture doth neceſſarily inforce theſe things.
<note n="*" place="margin">Or that thoſe El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were Lay-men?</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:35730:27"/>
               <note place="margin">Author to the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Majeſty.</note> And his followers, who with all their learning have endeavoured to extol his Tenents to the higheſt, have notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding acknowledged, that with whom the truth is they know not: neither do they all agree in one opinion: and of them which are at agreement, the moſt part through a courteous enducement have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed one man as their guide, and that one man therein moſt aſſuredly hath ſwerved from the Truth.</p>
            <p>And what can they be thought but ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeking ends in ſome, who when they know themſelves infinitely ſhort of that learning hath been in their Predeceſſors, and therefore not knowing how to get un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves fame, by walking in the plain and beaten road leading to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs marked out for them, will attempt to get unto themſelves a name, by pretending to have found out a nigher way unto it, then any elſe have done before them, &amp; amuzing the unlearneder ſort with a belief hereof, get unto themſelves followers after their own horrid inventions, whom they entice into ſuch a path, as neither our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> nor any of his holy Apoſtles ever traced out for them; &amp; inſenſibly by degrees bring
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35730:27"/>them into ſuch a Labyrinth, which when they are once entred into, they become a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, and know not which way to get out of it, and then run out of one error in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another, from bad, to worſe, till at length they become as dreadful Comets to all that behold them. Theſe kind of pernicious leaders imitate him, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not by any other act, ſet the Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> on fire, with an intent to memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize themſelves by that ſtrange one.</p>
            <p>And what can be thought better of theſe, than of that Monſter of men <hi>Bernardinus Ochinus,</hi> whoſe zeal at the firſt ſeemed to be ſo violent, as no former Religious inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, though never ſo rigorous, was ſtrict enough for him: he from thence fell to be an Heretick, then a Jew, then a Turk, and laſt of all an Atheiſt, and then wrote a furious invective againſt the three grand Impoſtors of the world, amongſt whom he ranked—<hi>Horreſco referens</hi>—<hi>Jeſus</hi> the Prince of Peace, <hi>Saviour</hi> of mankind, and <hi>Moſes</hi> as well as
<hi>Mahomet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what can they be conſtrued, but ſelf ſeeking ends in thoſe men, by whom thoſe who are rich, who are powerful and able to do either good or hurt, though <pb n="50" facs="tcp:35730:28"/>they be as ignorant and ſcandalous to the world, and perhaps more than thoſe who are poor, ſhall notwithſtanding be diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly invited, gladly received, and earneſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to partake of thoſe comfortable my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and ſaving food, which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of Mankind hath prepared for all true believers, without all peradventure, in as large a meaſure for thoſe indigent ones, to whom the Kingdome of Heaven belongs, as for thoſe great ones, who will find it eaſier for a Camel to enter thorow the eye of a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, than for the proud ever to come there.</p>
            <p>O let this ſlie generation of men know, who are guilty of this wilful omiſſion, and ſuch as upon unwarrantable pretences, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the holy
<hi>Sacrament</hi> of Baptiſm to thoſe it belongs to, and who thruſt by hungry and thirſty Souls from the ſaving banquet of of the Lords ſupper, who preferr obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ſelfiſh ends before the will of their Lord and Maker, that though they may take to themſelves the glorious name of Gods dear Children, it is to be feared, they may at laſt be found out to be Children of
<hi>Belial,</hi> in having in the day of their faſt ſought their own will, rather than the will of their great Commander; <pb n="51" facs="tcp:35730:28"/>let them take heed, that though in their own conceit they may be lifted up to Heaven, they be not brought down as low as Hell; for moſt aſſuredly it will be eaſier for thoſe in the Land of <hi>Sodom</hi> in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to enjoy the new Jeruſalem, than for obſtinate and ſelf-ſeeking Hypocrites to come within the gates thereof.</p>
            <p>Which kind of people profeſs to know <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.16.</note> but (it is to be feared) in their works deny him; they ſhut up the kingdom of Heaven before men, going not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor ſuffering thoſe that would enter to come in. They ſay, ſtand apart,
<note place="margin">Eſay 65.5.</note> come not near to us, for we are holier than you.
<note place="margin">Jer. 6.13.</note> Yet they bend their tongues like bowes for lies, and proceed from evil to worſe.
<note place="margin">Pro. 12.22.</note> Their lying lips are an abomination to the Lord, and their throats as open ſepulchers.
<note place="margin">Eſay 7.9.</note> Their hearts is as hard as the Adamant ſtone, and deceitful above all things:
<note place="margin">Eſay 9.16.</note> They are leaders of the People, cauſing them to err, and at laſt devour them.
<note place="margin">Eſay 15.26.</note> They lay wait as he that ſetteth ſnares, and make nets to catch men.
<note place="margin">Jude.</note> They have mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage.
<note place="margin">Eſay 5.16.</note> They draw iniquity with cords of vanity, and ſin with cart ropes. They are much given to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35730:29"/>be drunk with malice, though not with wine; and to ſtagger, their heads being full of whimſies, though not with ſtrong drink; which cauſeth them to be Eagle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyed in ſpying the mote in their brothers eye, and blind in beholding the beam that is in their own; they are ſtrainers at gnats, and ſwallowers of Camels.
<note place="margin">Eſay 59.5.</note> They hatch the Cockatrice egs, and weave the ſpiders web.
<note place="margin">64.6.</note> They are as an unclean thing, and their very righteouſneſs as a filthy clout. From the leaſt of them, to the greateſt, they are commonly given to Covetouſneſs,
<note place="margin">6.13.</note> and from the Prophet to the Prieſt they all deal falſly; the Prophets among them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a company of crafty fools, and the ſpiritual men no leſs then mad. Theſe are they which ſeparate themſelves from others, walking after their own luſts, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, complaining, mocking and ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king evil even of thoſe they know not. Clouds they are without water, carried about with every wind of doctrine, favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of damnable Hereſies, raging waves of the Sea foaming out their own ſhame, wandring ſtars to whom is reſerved the blackneſs of darkneſs for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But here by the by, we deſire there <pb n="53" facs="tcp:35730:29"/>may be notice taken, that it is no part of our thought, to bring within the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of this deſcription of Hypocrites, any truly ſincere and godly ſoul; neither have we the leaſt aim to any particular ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſons alive, that we are acquainted withal, and therefore if any ſhall account him or themſelves deciphered hereby, and thereupon take offence, it muſt neceſſarily ariſe, even in the opinion of all indifferent men, from the check of his or their own reſtleſs conſciences, which we heartily wiſh had no juſt cauſe to accuſe them, as we are truly innocent of any intent of doing ſo.</p>
            <p>We leave this way of accuſing &amp; cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring particular perſons, to that Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal generation of people, who being rapt up by a ſpiritual kind of pride into the aëry Region of a conceited degree of holineſs in themſelves, do from thence look upon others as ſenſual, polluted, and wicked, yea, as dogs and ſwine, altogether unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to eat with them either at their own or the Lords Table, or ſo much as to come within the verge of their ſelect compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
            <p>We thank our <hi>God</hi> we have not in ſuch
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35730:30"/>manner learned <hi>Chriſt</hi> as to place our ſelves in the ſeat of the Judg, accuſer, cenſurer or ſcorner of our Brethren; we ſhall leave all men to the great day of Judgment: for who is he that dares anticipate that day, and enter upon the throne of the great Judg? We confeſs that the ſerious acknowledgment of our own vileneſs makes us afraid at heart, that we our ſelves are the greateſt of ſinners; ſuch, as when we conſider our own deſervings, we cannot but tremble with terror, and amazement at the juſt and dreadful puniſhment due unto us for ſin, and hereby have learned to pity others as fellow ſinners, &amp; not think our ſelves too good to accompany them in civil, or religious duties.</p>
            <p>Wee do withgreif, and ſhameconfeſs, that we have erred willingly, and ſtrayed willingly from the wayes of our Almighty and moſt merciful Father, and that more like untamed Buls then loſt and wandring ſheep, we have followed too much even altogether the abſurd devices, and brutiſh deſires of our own hearts, we have been offended againſt, nay been offended at his holy, moſt holy laws, we have left undone, not lone at all thoſe things which we ought <pb n="55" facs="tcp:35730:30"/>to have done, but inſteed thereof done thoſe things which we ſhould not have done, inſomuch as there is no health, no hope of health in us miſerable, moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and the greateſt of ſinners: all which when we ſeriouſly lay to our guilty conſciences, how can we poſſibly preferr our own wicked, and abominable ſelves, whom we certainly know to be thus pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and defiled, before others, whoſe hearts we are no way ſo able to ſearch and dive into, as we may into our own?</p>
            <p>And being in ſo great a meaſure ſinful, from the crown of our heads to the ſoles of our feet all over contaminated and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, in ſo much as no part of us remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſound, we know no certain cure for our ſick and wounded ſouls, laden with ſo many and ſo grevious ſins, but to caſt our ſelves into the arms of our moſt bleſſed Redeemer, and by a lively faith (though we cannot as Saints, yet) lay claim unto him as ſinners, (as wounded and penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) whom he came to ſave; and his coming being to ſave ſuch, he will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afford the ſeals of his Grace to ſuch, and having appointed the Miniſters of his Goſpel to deliver them to ſuch, we look <pb n="56" facs="tcp:35730:31"/>upon you (Mr.
<hi>Barton</hi>) if you be a Miniſter of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> as bound in duty (having thruſt your ſelf upon us, and thereby kept off thoſe who might otherwiſe have done it) to perform your office, according to the diſpenſation of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.25.</note> which is given to his Miniſters to us ward to fulfil the word of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we alſo ſay to you as the Apoſtle commands the Church of
<hi>God</hi> to ſay to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 4.17.</note> Take heed to the Miniſtry that thou haſt received in the Lord, that thou fulful it: a part whereof is the Communication of the <hi>Sacraments</hi> of the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which (we wiſh we had no cauſe to ſay ſo) to our greif, and your own ſhame, you have hitherto omitted.</p>
            <p>And therefore give us leave to tell you that the Miniſters total omiſſion of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the <hi>Sacraments</hi> to the generality of the people under his charge, becauſe there may perhaps ſome wicked perſons, not known to be ſcandalous creep in amongſt the Godly, is, as an erroneous, ſo an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart way, never uſed in the Church, from the time of the firſt planting of it, till of latter dayes the wild Boar of the foreſt hath ruſhed into <hi>Chriſts</hi> vineyard, to the <pb n="57" facs="tcp:35730:31"/>danger of the rooting out of the hearts of men the zeal to the frequent practiſe of applying the ſeals of Grace to their ſouls; and inſteed thereof to the planting of a peculiar and ſuperſtitious holineſs in the Ordinances, thereby quite to invert the charitable uſe of them, and to bereave them of the great Legacy which the <hi>Saviour</hi> of the world hath left to his people.</p>
            <p>And we do wonder there can be any perſon ſo obſtinate and ſelfiſh, as thereby to have the eyes of his underſtanding ſo blinded, to force himſelf to believe that an upſtart unuſed way, ſhould be the right way, when <hi>God</hi> himſelf hath ſaid, Ask for the old way, and with all told us, that it is the good way, &amp; given us a charge that we ſhould walk in that way, with a promiſe, that in ſo doing, we ſhould find reſt to our ſouls.</p>
            <p>He hath alſo ſaid by his Scripture for our inſtruction, Call to remembrance the dayes of old, ask thy Fathers and they will ſhew thee, ask thy Elders and they will tell thee.</p>
            <p>And now can any man (who is not utterly void of reaſon) think that He for whom it is impoſſible to lie, hath promiſed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35730:32"/>reſt unto our ſouls by our walking in the old way, and hath promiſed to guide his Church all wayes in the right way, ſhould notwithſtanding break his word, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to wander out of the way, and that for above 16 hundred years together, even till theſe times, theſe very latter, and perrillous times, in which the ſpirit ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth evidently, that there ſhould come divers Hypocrites, men having their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſeared with a hot iron, who ſhould depart from the faith, giving heed to the ſpirit of error. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Jude</hi>
19.</p>
            <p>And ſhall that ſpirit of error have ſo much power, as contrary to Gods directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to intice us into new wayes, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading us to imbrace novel opinions, or unwarrantable practices in Religion, ſchiſmes or hereſies? ſhall any, under any plauſible pretence whatſoever, go about to make us believe that the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> are not neceſſary to Salvation, or that the Celebration of them doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Miniſterial Office, we ſhall boldly aver ſuch to be of Yeſterday, and not to be yet come to their underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:35730:32"/>And we ſhall not be aſhamed to ſay, they are altogether out of the old right way, and have made to themſelves crooked pathes, wherein they grope as blind men, without eyes, and ſtumble at noon-day as in the twi-light, their feet treading the pavements of deſolation and deſtruction, run to evil, far off from the way of peace and equity; which, it ſhould ſeem, they never would be enduced to follow; which is the reaſon why judgment is ſo far from them, and juſtice comes not neer them.</p>
            <p>And we do here for our ſelves profeſs, that if an Angel ſhould come from heaven, and preach to us any doctrine in order to the putting us out of the right way, we would neither follow nor believe him.</p>
            <p>For as it hath been hitherto, ſo ſhall it be ever far from us, of the Pariſh of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> in theſe licentious times, in which ſome would have the golden reines of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and government let looſe in the Church, in ſo much that ſingle Miniſters and private perſons might take up what forme of divine worſhip they pleaſed to follow: ſo dangerous an example, far be it from us, to be led by; wandring ſtars, new, but falſe lights; bold, but blind <pb n="60" facs="tcp:35730:33"/>guides: far be it from us to make ſmall or no account of the pretious Ordinances of our Lord and
<hi>Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> by neglecting the holy Sacrament of Baptiſm, and by counting the blood of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as an unholy thing: far be it from us, to exchange the truth which we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, for falſhood which ought not to be believed; or to undervalue the ſound doctrine which hath been taught us, by giving ear to old wives tales: for it is our firm reſolution to imbrace that truth, which the great Doctor and Author of truth it ſelf, hath commanded, the bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught, the holy Martyrs confirmed, and the moſt godly, and moſt learned men in all ages, practiſed; we ſhall deſire to be waſhed, that we may be cleanſed, we ſhall deſire to eat that we may live.</p>
            <p>Thus much have we thought fitting to declare, to the end that poſterity, as well as thoſe now living, might know what our Judgments are, concerning the ſacred and ſaving Ordinances which our moſt bleſſed
<hi>Saviour</hi> (whoſe name be for ever praiſed) hath left to his
<hi>Church,</hi> and that in a time in which ſo ſlight a regard hath been had of his heavenly <hi>Myſteries</hi> we did <pb n="61" facs="tcp:35730:33"/>not with ſilence, and patience behold ſuch horrible contempt, and deteſtable neglect: but on the other ſide might underſtand our reverend eſteem, and opinion of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and uſe of thoſe Seals, that are to continue in his <hi>Church,</hi> until <hi>He,</hi> the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of them, come to Judg the <hi>World,</hi> and that a more free and large admiſſion ought to be to them, than of late hath been permitted, or allowed of: and alſo that obſtinacy and ſelfiſh ends have been ſtumbling blocks in the way to this free admiſſion, and that Tyrannical Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of ſome, which hath caſt thoſe ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocks in, is both new in erection, and erroneous in execution.</p>
            <p>And as we have declared thus much, ſo we thought our ſelves bound in conſcience to do it, to the end that we might not foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly, like the unprofitable ſervant, hide our Talent in a Napkin, or perfidiouſly put our light under a buſhel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non nobis nati ſumus,</hi> was the ſaying of a Heathen, we are not born for the good of our ſelves alone, but for the welfare of others alſo; &amp; we ſay of our very Enemies, as well as friends; to whom we have in ſome meaſure held out our light, as we <pb n="62" facs="tcp:35730:34"/>have done to our neereſt Relations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may (if they pleaſe) ſee how to diſtinguiſh realities from apparances, ſubſtances from ſhadowes, truth from falſhood.</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding though they may have but little or no regard to our care, &amp; endeavours for their good; nay, though as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> they may ſtand in direct oppoſition to, and contradiction againſt us, yet ſhall not we ſay with the great Cardinal, <hi>Si populus vult decipi, decipiatur,</hi> (If the people will be deceived let them be ſo,) but ſhall, to the utmoſt of our power, prevent ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, and as much as in us lies, guide their feet in the bleſſed wayes of truth and peace.</p>
            <p>And in Order thereunto ſhall adviſe them, as we do the like to all others, of what condition, and quality ſoever they be, to beware of ſuch as come in ſheeps clothing; and to mark thoſe who make diviſion, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced in the old Maxime, <hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> Divide and Command.</p>
            <p>Of ſuch it hath been ſaid of old, <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi vulpes in deſerto Prophetae tui, O Iſrael:</hi> O Iſrael thy Prophets are like Foxes in <pb n="63" facs="tcp:35730:34"/>the deſert: and it is juſtly to be feared, that ſome of that breed, are crept in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</p>
            <p>Of whom that we may the better take heed, we ſhall continually and fervently pray to <hi>Almighty God,</hi> to give us a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſpirit, and a right apprehenſion of the neceſſary uſe of his holy, heavenly and ſaving myſteries, ſo as we may not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect, much leſs contemn them, but fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and piouſly hunger and thirſt after them, and withal that we may not be <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joled</hi> by the ſelfiſh ends of any erring Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians or others, how ſeemingly-holy ſoever they be, that we may be able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne wolves clothed like ſheep, and that he will arm us with the wiſdome of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, whereby we may underſtand and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the ſubtilties and deceipts of thoſe foxes, who earneſtly deſire to prey upon our goods and intellects, that ſo being ſafe under the ſhadow of our moſt Gracious Protectors wings, we may humbly, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly and joyfully worſhip him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing unto him all Honor, Power, and Dominion both now and for ever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35730:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35730:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
